Hello and welcome back to Synchro.
Think about the last job interview you had.
You probably tried to present yourself as outgoing, energetic,
a team player who thrives in collaborative environments.
Even if you're someone who does their best thinking alone.
Even if small talk drains you.
Even if you'd rather spend your lunch break reading the networking.
We've been taught that success,
especially in our careers, belongs to the extroverts.
But what if everything you've been told about introversion
and extroversion is not just wrong,
but actively harming your career potential?
Carl Jong, the Swiss psychiatrist who first coined these terms,
had a radically different
understanding of what introversion and extroversion actually mean.
And more importantly,
he understood how each type, when properly leveraged,
possesses
unique strengths that can lead to extraordinary professional success.
Today, we're going deep into Jungian typology to understand
not just what your type is,
but how to use it strategically to build a career that doesn't drain
you but energizes you.
By the end of this video, you'll understand why forcing yourself to be
someone you're not is the worst career strategy possible,
and how aligning your work with your psychological type can unlock
levels of success and satisfaction you didn't know were possible.
Let's dive in.
Before we can leverage your Jungian type, we need to understand
what Junge actually meant by introversion and extroversion.
Because it's probably not what you think.
In popular culture,
these terms have been reduced to simple social preferences.
Extroverts are outgoing and talkative.
Introverts are shy and quiet.
But Jong's original concept was far more sophisticated
and far more useful for career development.
For Jong introversion and extroversion weren't about social skills
or preference for parties versus solitude.
They were about the fundamental orientation of your psychic energy.
They described where you naturally direct your attention
and from where you draw your vitality.
Jun wrote that the introverts interest flows inward toward the subject,
toward their own
internal psychological processes, ideas, impressions and reactions.
The introvert is oriented
primarily toward the inner world of thoughts, feelings and reflections.
Their energy moves from the outer world inward, where it gets processed,
contemplated and given meaning before any outward action occurs.
The extrovert, by contrast, has their interest flowing outward
toward the object, toward people.
Things and external events.
The extrovert is oriented primarily
toward the outer world of action, interaction and tangible reality.
Their energy moves from inner experience, outward finding expression
and vitality through engagement with external environment.
Notice what Jong isn't saying.
He's not saying
introverts hate people or that extroverts can't think deeply.
He's describing the natural flow of psychic energy and attention.
An introvert can be socially skilled, charismatic, even, but
they'll need time alone afterward to process the experience internally.
An extrovert can engage in deep reflection,
but they'll often need to talk through their thoughts with others
or take action to fully understand what they're thinking.
This distinction is crucial for your career because it determines
what kinds of work environments,
tasks and roles will energize you versus drain you.
Let's make this concrete with an example.
Consider two marketing professionals, David and Jennifer.
David is an introvert.
He does his best creative work when he can research, deeply develop
comprehensive strategies and refine his ideas before presenting them.
He's excellent in one on one client meetings where depth of relationship
matters.
He's the person who sends the follow up email that perfectly captures
what was discussed and moves the project forward.
His presentations are thoroughly prepared, insightful and impactful.
Jennifer is an extrovert.
She generates her best ideas in brainstorming sessions,
bouncing concepts off colleagues in real time.
She's energized by client calls,
networking events and collaborative workshops.
She thinks out loud, tests ideas through conversation and adapts quickly
based on immediate feedback.
Her presentations are dynamic, responsive to the room,
and create immediate engagement.
Both are excellent at marketing, but they're leveraging
completely different cognitive and energetic processes.
The tragedy is that many organizations only recognize
and reward Jennifer's style, leaving talented introverts
like David feeling inadequate or trying to force themselves
into an extroverted mold that depletes them.
Here's the key insight that Young emphasized.
Neither type is superior.
Each has profound strengths and endeavor knowable limitations.
The question isn't which type is better for your career,
but how to structure your career around your types
Natural strengths while managing its weaknesses.
Let's explore the specific career advantages of each type,
starting with introversion.
Young observed that introverts excel at depth over breadth
because their energy flows inward.
They're naturally inclined toward sustained focus as complex problem
solving and developing expertise.
They're often the people who become true masters of their craft
because they're willing to spend hours,
days, years
going deep into their subject matter in practical career terms.
This means introverts often excel in roles requiring specialized
knowledge, strategic thinking and independent work.
Research Scientists.
Software Developers. Writers. Analysts.
Financial planners, architects and academic researchers are fields
where introverted strengths shine.
But it's not limited to solitary professions.
Many successful executives, lawyers and consultants are introverts
who've learned to leverage their natural inclination
toward careful analysis and thoughtful decision making.
Introverts also tend to be excellent listeners,
which is an underrated career superpower.
While an extrovert might be formulating their response, while
you're talking, the introvert is genuinely taking in what you're saying.
Processing it and forming a considered response.
This makes them exceptional. Counselors.
Coaches interview doers and advisors.
People feel heard and understood,
which builds deep professional relationships and trust.
Another advantage is that introverts are less dependent
on external validation for their motivation.
They're driven more by internal standards of excellence
and personal satisfaction with their work.
This can lead to more sustainable career satisfaction because
they're not constantly seeking approval or recognition from others.
They can weather periods
where their contributions aren't immediately visible or celebrated.
However, introverts face predictable career challenges.
They may struggle with self-promotion, networking events
and making their accomplishments visible in organizations
that reward vocal participation.
They might be overlooked for leadership roles because they don't fit
the stereotypical image of the charismatic, outgoing leader.
They can experience burnout in environments with constant meetings,
open plan offices, or an expectation of immediate responsiveness.
Now let's look at extroverted strengths.
Jung noted that extroverts excel at breadth over depth
because their energy flows outward.
They're naturally inclined toward building.
Networks generate doing ideas through interaction and taking action.
They're energized by variety stimulation and engagement
with people and projects in career terms.
Extroverts often thrive in roles
requiring relationship building, communication
and dynamic problem
solving sales, business development, public relations,
teaching, event management, hospitality and entrepreneurship are fields
where extroverted strengths shine.
But again, it's not limited.
Many successful researchers, engineers and analysts are extroverts
who leverage their ability to collaborate, share ideas
and build teams around their work.
Extroverts are typically skilled at networking,
not in a superficial way,
but because they're genuinely energized by meeting new people
and exploring connections.
This creates career opportunities that might never appear on job boards.
They hear about positions through their network.
Get introductions to key decision makers and build relationships
that open doors throughout their career.
Another advantage is that extroverts
tend to be comfortable with visibility and self-promotion.
They can articulate their ideas and accomplishments
without feeling like they're bragging in organizational settings.
This means their work gets noticed.
They're top of mind for new opportunities,
and they're often perceived as leadership material.
Extroverts also excel at thinking on their feet
and adapting to changing circumstances.
They process information through external engagement,
which means they can handle dynamic situations,
pivot strategies in real time, and respond to feedback immediately.
This is invaluable in fast paced environments and crisis situations.
However, extroverts face their own challenges.
They may struggle with roles
requiring extended periods of solitary focused work.
They might find it difficult to develop deep expertise
because they're drawn to variety and new experiences.
They can make hasty decisions because their bias is toward action.
Rather than reflection,
they might also experience burnout in environments that are too isolated
or where they lack opportunities for collaboration and interaction.
Here's where Jong's insight becomes career changing.
The goal isn't to overcome your type, but to leverage it.
This means three things First, choosing roles and environments
that align with your type strengths.
Second, developing strategies to manage your types challenges.
Third, understanding that you can access your non-preferred orientation
when needed, but it will cost more energy.
Let's start with role selection.
If you're an introvert, look for positions that allow for deep work
independent projects and meaningful one on one interactions.
This doesn't mean avoiding all teamwork or client contact,
but ensuring these aren't constant.
Look for organizations that value written communication.
Give time for thoughtful responses
and don't mistake quiet for disengagement.
Consider roles like research analyst, Technical specialist,
Strategic planner, content creator, or backend developer.
Even in traditionally extroverted fields,
look for the introverted niches in sales.
Consider technical sales
where product expertise matters more than schmoozing in management.
Consider project management or operations roles
rather than business development.
If you're an extrovert, look for positions with variety.
Interact and opportunities to think through conversation.
Seek organizations with collaborative cultures.
Open communication and value for relationship building.
Consider roles like Account Manager, Business development, Team Leader.
Trainer, recruiter or consultant.
Even in traditionally introverted fields,
find the extroverted angles in software development.
Consider product management or developer relations in research.
Consider roles involving collaboration, presentation,
or translation of technical findings for broader audiences.
Now let's talk about managing your challenges.
If you're an introvert, your biggest career
liability is often invisibility.
You might do excellent work that no one knows about.
The solution isn't to become an extrovert,
but to create systems for visibility.
Schedule regular one on one updates with your manager
where you can discuss your work in depth.
Document your contributions in writing
where you're more comfortable articulating your value.
Choose one or two networking events per quarter
rather than trying to attend everything.
Prepare specific talking points about your projects
so you're not caught off guard.
Find an extroverted mentor or colleague
who can help advocate for your work.
Another challenge for introverts
is the energy drain of excessive meetings and collaboration.
Build boundaries around your deep work time.
BLOCK off your calendar for focused work periods.
Negotiate for some remote work days
if possible, even in hybrid environments.
Take real breaks between meetings to recharge.
Learn to say I need to think about this and get back to you
rather than feeling pressured to respond and immediately.
If you're an extrovert, your biggest career
liability might be perceived superficiality or lack of follow through.
Your great at starting things and generating ideas,
but may struggle with the sustained
focus needed to execute The solution is to build systems for depth.
Partner with introverted colleagues who excel at implementation.
Use project management tools that help you track details.
Schedule regular reflection time to process what you're learning.
Force yourself to do deeper research before meetings
rather than relying solely on thinking out loud.
Find an introverted mentor
who can model deep expertise and sustained focus.
Another challenge for extroverts
is managing your energy in roles requiring extended focus.
If you're in a position
requiring significant independent work, build in collaborative breaks.
Schedule working sessions with colleagues,
even if you're working on different projects.
Take calls while walking.
Process your thoughts through voice memos, or by teaching someone else
what you're learning.
Join professional groups or committees
that give you regular interaction outside your core work.
Here's the advanced insight.
You also taught that we each have access to both orientations,
but one is conscious and developed
while the other remains more unconscious and primitive.
He called the less developed orientation the inferior function.
Understanding this is crucial because your inferior function
will emerge under stress, often in dysfunctional ways.
For introverts under stress, the inferior extroversion
might emerge as uncharacterized stick outbursts,
desperate networking attempts, or manic social activity
that leads to exhaustion.
If you find yourself suddenly trying to connect with everyone
oversharing
or making impulsive commitments,
you might be in the grip of your inferior function.
The solution is to return to your dominant, introverted approach
first process what's happening internally,
then engage with others more intentionally.
For extroverts under stress,
the inferior introversion might emerge as withdrawal, brooding,
pessimistic rumination or paralysis through over analysis.
If you find yourself unusually isolated, unable to make decisions
or trapped in negative
thought loops, you might be in the grip of your inferior function.
The solution is to return to your dominant, extroverted approach.
First, talk through what's happening with trusted others.
Take action. Even if imperfect, then reflect more carefully.
Once you've regained equilibrium, the most successful people aren't
those who've mastered both orientation as equally.
There are those who fully develop their dominant orientation
while learning when and how to access their non-dominant orientation.
And strategically,
an introverted leader learns to give energizing public presentations
by preparing thoroughly and building in recovery time.
And extroverted analyst learns to produce deep research by partnering
with others during the process and scheduling reflection time.
Let me share a historical example.
Albert Einstein was clearly an introvert.
He did his best thinking in solitude, often
taking long walks alone to work through problems.
He famously said that he rarely thought in words at all.
But in images and feelings that he only later translated to language.
His greatest breakthroughs came from sustained, solitary contemplation.
But Einstein also recognized
when he needed to access his extroverted side.
He gave lectures, engaged in vigorous debates with colleagues,
and used conversation to test and refine his ideas.
He didn't try to become an extrovert, but he strategically deployed
extroverted behaviors when they served his work.
And crucially, he structured his life and career to maximize his
introverted strengths while minimizing situations that would drain him.
Conversely, Richard Branson is clearly an extrovert.
He's energized by people, builds businesses through relationships,
and makes decisions through action and feedback.
He's dyslexic and, by his own admission, not naturally inclined toward
deep, solitary analysis of written material.
But he's built a business empire by leveraging his extroverted
strengths, surrounding himself with detail oriented introverts
who complement his style
and creating organizational structures that play to his type.
Both are wildly successful, not despite their type,
but because they fully leveraged it.
This is the career strategy that Jung's typology suggests.
Know yourself deeply.
Structure your career around your strengths.
Develop strategies for your challenges
and access your non-preferred orientation
strategically, rather than trying to become someone you're not.
So here's your action plan.
First, honestly, assess your type.
Don't base this on whether you're shy or outgoing,
but on where your energy naturally flows.
Do you need to process experiences internally before acting,
or do you process through external engagement?
Do you find depth energizing or draining?
Do you prefer variety or sustained focus?
Be honest, not aspirational.
Second, audit your current role and work environment.
Does it align with your type strengths
or constantly force you into your weaker orientation?
If you're an introvert in a role with constant meetings
and interruptions and or an extrovert in an isolated position,
you're fighting uphill.
Consider how you might reshape your current role,
or whether it's time to find a better fit.
Third, develop your type specific career strategies.
Introverts should focus on building
deep expertise, ease creating systems for visibility,
and finding roles where thoughtfulness is valued.
Extroverts should focus on leveraging networks, partnering with detail
oriented colleagues,
and finding roles where relationship building drives success.
Fourth, learn to recognize
when you're in the grip of your inferior function under stress.
Instead of pushing harder in the wrong direction,
return to your dominant orientation
to regain equilibrium, then engage
your non-preferred side more skillfully.
Fifth, find mentors and colleagues who complement your type.
Introverts benefit from extroverted advocates
who can champion their work.
Extroverts benefit from introverted colleagues
who can help with follow through and depth.
The most successful teams aren't all one type,
but leverage the strengths of both.
Carl Jung believed that the ultimate goal
of psychological development was individuation
becoming fully yourself
rather than conforming to collective expectations.
This applies profoundly to career development.
The path to professional success
and satisfaction isn't becoming the person you think employers want.
It's becoming more fully the person you actually are
and finding or creating roles where that person can thrive.
Your career shouldn't be a daily battle against your nature.
It should be an expression of your nature
when you stop trying to force yourself into an ill fitting mold
and instead leverage your union type work becomes energizing
rather than draining.
You develop genuine competitive advantages because you're operating
from your strengths rather than constantly managing weaknesses.
You find sustainable success
because you're not burning energy pretending to be someone you're not.
The career advice industry often sells a one size fits
all vision of success.
Be bold. Network. Constantly promote yourself.
Think big. Move fast.
But for introverts,
this formula is exhausting and often counterproductive.
The same industry sometimes tells extroverts to slow down.
Focus more.
Stop chasing shiny objects.
But for many extroverts, this advice fights their natural gifts.
Jung offers a different path.
Understand your type deeply leverage
its inherent strengths to manage its predictable challenges
and access your non-preferred orientation strategically when needed.
This is how you build not just a successful career,
but a career that actually fits who you are.
So here's your challenge this week.
Identify one way your current work situation is forcing you
to operate constantly in your non-preferred orientation.
Then brainstorm one structural change
that would allow you to leverage your natural type more effectively.
Maybe it's negotiating for more focused work time or more collaborative
projects, or a different communication style with your team.
Whatever it is, take one action
toward aligning your work with your type.
The career you're meant to have isn't the one that requires you
to become someone else.
It's the one that allows you to become more fully yourself.
Thank you for watching. Let me know in the comments.
Whether you're an introvert or extrovert
and what career strategies have worked for you.
And as always, I'll see you in the next video.